RG 058, Research Commission
Connecticut State Library
Research Commission records
1964-1971
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Research Commission
30.5 cubic feet
The Research Commission supported and encouraged research and related activities "relevant to the interests and welfare or the economic betterment of the citizens of Connecticut."
RG058
T002718
Historical Note
The General Assembly established the Connecticut Research Commission in June 1965. Its establishment followed the recommendations of the final report (June 1965) of the Connecticut Advisory Committee, which Governor John Dempsey had established in April 1961. That Committee had itself been the result of recommendations of the Economic Planning and Development Committee ("Maxey Committee") in December 1960.
The Research Commission's principal function was to support and encourage research and related activities "relevant to the interests and welfare or the economic betterment of the citizens of Connecticut." The appointed ten-member Commission met monthly to determine policy and agree on priorities for the allocation of funds. The Director, John S. Burlew, and a small staff administered the Commission that was based primarily on the award of research support grants and contracts for research work. Projects covered many fields, including many related to research development and the quality of the environment. Governor Thomas Meskill stopped the allocation of funds after December 31, 1970, and the Commission died on August 5, 1971.
Scope and Content
Project applications contain formal requests for support for projects, with supporting data, together with related correspondence. Research support award files contain applications, supporting data, related corresopndence, and interim, progress and final reports on projects supported by the Commission. Student research support award files contain reports and related materials pertaining to projects under the student research program. Contract files contain contracts with professional research and engineering firms, with related proposals, corresopndence and reports. Minutes of meetings contain typed copies of minutes of the monthly Commission meetings, as well as a folder of Direcotr Burlew's notes. The main reading file is that of Dr. John S. Burlew, Director. Reading files for other staff are also present. Press releases contain Mimeographed or printed press releases by the Commission, announcing research awards or pertaining to other newsworthy matters. The General file contains correspondence, reports, minutes, notes, memoranda and reference materials pertaining to the work and interests of the Commission. The Financial files contain vouchers, invoices, allotment advices, appropriation and expendiiture statements and related documents, notes and correspondence pertaining to the accounts and financial administration of the Commission.
Arrangement
Series 1. Project applications, 1965-1971
Series 2. Research award support files, 1965-1971.
Series 3. Student research support award files, 1971.
Series 4. Contract award files, 1965-1971.
Series 5. Minutes of meetings, 1965-1970.
Series 6. Memoranda from director to commission members, 1966-1970.
Series 7. Reading files, 1966-1971.
Series 8. Press releases, 1966-1970.
Series 9. General file, 1965-1971.
Series 9. Financial files, 1964-1969.
Related Material
RG 005:034, John N. Dempsey gubernatorial records
The following folders from Box A-251:
Economic Planning & Development Committee (Booz, Alan & Hamilton Report Implementation) [1966]
Economic Planning and Development Committee (Mr. Ellis Maxey, Chair) [1960-1965]
The following folders from Box A-290:
Research Advisory Committee (2 folders) [1961-1970]
Research Commission (2 folders) [1965-1967]
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. Research Commission
Persons:
Burlew, John S.
Subjects:
Connecticut. Research Commission -- Records and correspondence; Research, Industrial -- Research grants -- Connecticut; Technological innovations -- Research grants -- Connecticut
Document Types:
Correspondence; Financial records; Lists; Memorandums; Minutes; Press releases; Reports
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
The Development Commission took over the Commission's papers and some residual responsibilities and turned over project proposals, award files and some contract files to the State Library in July 1972. The other records listed below came from the Comptroller. Some records - primarily pertaining to personnel and financial management - remained with the Development Commission. The Development Commission is now the Department of Economic and Community Development.
Container List
- Series 1. Project applications, 1965-1971
  Arranged numerically by proposal number 1-391. Proposal numbers also inclupde an 8-digit coded identification of source, date of receipt and dollar value. For example, proposal 55 is numbered P-01056711-55.
  Listed below are the proposal number, institution, subject, and Commission action with date of action.
  - P-1, Yale University, Lab for study of surfaces, Granted 1966 March 18 (Box 1)
  - P-2, New England Institute, Energy exchange, Granted 1966 July 15 (Box 1)
  - P-3, State Board Conneccticut Colleges, Academic plans, Declined 1966 August 19 (Box 1)
  - P-4, University of Connecticut, 5-year plan State Technical Services, Declined 1966 March 18 (Box 1)
  - P-5, Connecticut Education TV, On-the-job training, Granted 1966 June 17 (Box 1)
  - P-6, Connecticut State Library, Connecticut Library Research Center (Box 1)
  - P-7, Fairfield University, Information services, Declined 1966 March 18 (Box 1)
  - P-8, University of Connecticut, Well field, Granted 1966 April 19 (Box 1)
  - P-9, University of Connecticut, Heat transfer, Declined, 1966 May 20 (Box 1)
  - P-10, Comm. Council New Haven, Study of services, Declined 1966 October 21 (Box 1)
  - P-12, University of Connecticut, Farmington River shad, Granted 1966 May 20 (Box 1)
  - P-13, University of Connecticut, Growth of industries, Declined 1966 July 15 (Box 1)
  - P-14, University of Connecticut, Histaminopexis, Granted 1966 June 17 (Box 1)
  - P-15, University of Connecticut, Early land plants, Declined 1966 May 20 (Box 1)
  - P-16, Connecticut Society Medical Research, Status of Medical research, Declined 1966 May 20 (Box 1)
  - P-17, Renssalaer Polytechnic Institute, High energy beam, Granted 1966, July 15 (Box 1)
  - P-18, Yale University, Vac-UV Instr. Granted 1966 August 19 (Box 1)
  - P-19, Connecticut State Library, Connecticut Library Res. Center, Approved, 1966 May 20 (Box 1)
  - P-20, University of Connecticut, Race, school public attention, Declined, 1966 October 21 (Box 1)
  - P-21, Fairfield University, Government-to-citizen communications, Declined 1966 June 17 (Box 1)
  - P-22, Yale University, Attitude & behavior patterns R&D organizations, Approved, 1966 October 21 (Box 1)
  - P-23, General Dynamics/Electric Boad, Revitilze Connecticut fishing industry, Granted, 1966 June 17 (Box 1)
  - P-24, UAC Research Laboratories, Model for rapid transit system, Deemed withdrawn, 1967 Mary 17 (Box 1)
  - P-25, Regional Advisory Committee, Regional information handling services, Granted 1966 November 18 (Box 1)
  - P-26, Travelers Research Center, Air pollution, Granted 1966 September 16 (Box 1)
  - P-27, Connecticut Society Medical Research, Held for future information (Box 1)
  - P-28, Mental Health Department, Socio-economic study of mental health patients, Granted 1966 September 16 (Box 1)
  - P-29, Wesleyan University, Inter-inst.curricula in environmental studies, Declined, 1966 September 16 (Box 1)
  - P-30, UAC Research Laboratories, Sewage treatment, Prov. award withdrawn 1967 August 29 (Box 1)
  - P-31, New England Institute, Gaseous ion formation, Declined 1967 September 29 (Box 1)
  - P-32, University of Connecticut, Numerical control machine tools, Declined 1967 June 16 (Box 1)
  - P-33, University of Bridgeport, Center for Application of Materials & Processes, Declined 1966 November 18 (Box 1)
  - P-34, University of Connecticut, Electron diffraction studies, Declined, 1967 July 21 (Box 1)
  - P-35, University of Connecitcut, Bioengineering laborary, Granted, 1967 July 21 (Box 1)
  - P-36, URIC, Child welfare, Granted 1966 November 18 (Box 1)
  - P-37, Yale University, Hydrogeochemistry Linsley Pond, Declined 1966 Novemeber 18 (Box 1)
  - P-38, Yale University, Induction/isolation mutants, Granted 1967 January 20 (Box 1)
  - P-39, Yale University, Food for oyster larvae, Granted 1967 February 17 (Box 1)
  - P-40, University of Bridgeport, Materials Processing Research, Granted 1966 December 16 (Box 1)
  - P-41, Yale University, Isotopic dating studies, Granted 1967 June 16 (Box 1)
  - P-42, American Cyanamid, Connecticut oysters, Granted 1967 May 18 (Box 1)
  - P-43, Mitchell College, Radiation on rice, Granted 1967 May 19, not accepted (Box 1)
  - P-44, Trinity College, Auto exhaust gases, Granted 1967 June 16 (Box 1)
  - P-45, UAC-Research, Survey of transportation, Declined 1967 September 29 (Box 1)
  - P-46, University of Connecticut, Water permeation, Granted 1967 June 16 (Box 1)
  - P-47, Mental Health Department, Alcoholism rehabilitation, Withdrawn 1968 August 15 (Box 1)
  - P-48, URIC, Research potential with Connecticut industry business & government, Granted 1967 March 17 (Box 1)
  - P-49, Kaman, Transportation center, Declined 1967 July 21 (Box 1)
  - P-50, University of Connecticut, Reading and psychomotor disability, Declined 1967 October 20 (Box 1)
  - P-51, University of Hartford, Solid waste disposal system, Granted 1967 May 19 (Box 1)
  - P-52, University of Connecticut, Correctional Manpower Education & Training, Withdrawn 1967 June 7 (Box 1)
  - P-53, Meyers Electro/Cooling Products, Central disposal facilities for liquid wastes, Declined 1967 July 21 (Box 1)
  - P-54, Meyers Electro/Cooling Products, Central disposal system for oil-based liquid wastes, Declined, 1967 May 19 (Box 1)
  - P-55, University of Connecticut, Synchronized electric and magnetic fields, Declined 1967 July 21 (Box 1)
  - P-56, Yale University, Connecticut hardwoods, Granted 1967 July 21 (Box 1)
  - P-57, Travelers Research Center, Inc., Industrial waste, Declined 1967 July 21 (Box 1)
  - P-58, Yale University, Relation of structure to function in transfer RNA, Declined 1967 July 21 (Box 1)
  - P-59,. Trendex, Inc., Citizen participation in government, Declined 1967 October 20 (Box 1)
  - P-60, Lovejoy Associates, Productivity of insurance companies, Declined 1967 October 20 (Box 1)
  - P-61, University of Hartford, Mobile noise measurement laboratory, Granted 1967 Novemnber 17 (Box 1)
  - P-62, Travelers Research Center, Disposal of liquid industrial wastes, Declined 1967 October 20 (Box 1)
  - P-63, James S. Minges & Associates, Disposal of liquid industrial wastes, Declined 1967 October 20 (Box 1)
  - P-64. Lancy Laboratories, Inc., Disposal of liquid industrial wastes, declined 1967 September 29 (Box 1)
  - P-65, C. W. Blakeslee & Sons, Inc., Disposal of liquid industrial wastes, Declined 1967 September 29 (Box 1)
  - P-66, Combustion Engineering, Inc., Disposal of liquid industrial wastes, Declined 1967 October 20 (Box 1)
  - P-67, New England Institute for Medical Research, Interdisciplinary approach to energy exchange, Approved 1967 Septemnber 29 (Box 1)
  - P-68, P.W. Genovese & Associates - Royal Industrial Research, Disposal opf liquid industrial wastes, Declined 1967 September 29 (Box 1)
  - P-69, Fairfield University, Analysis for corrosive gases, Granted 1967 December 15 (Box 1)
  - P-70, Wesleyan University, Improvement of the 20-inch telescope, Granted 1967 December 15 (Box 1)
  - P-71, University of Connecticut, Role of forest in open space planning in Eastern Connecticut, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-72, Yale University, Reactions and structures of organometallic compounds, Granted 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-73, TRC, Inc., Theoretical study of the stability of fluid flow, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-74, Central Connecticut State College, Feasibility of using undergraduate student research teams as approach to solution of social problems in Connecticut, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-75, City of New Haven, Effectiveness of program budgeting in local government, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-76, Geitz Engineering, Smog removal and weather control - chimneys, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-77, University of Connecticut, Lifetimes of excited molecular vibrational states, Granted 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-78, University of Bridgeport, Oral history archive, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-79, University of Connecticut, Inelastic atom-atom collisions, Granted 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-80, TRC, Inc., R & D applied to police departments, Granted 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-81, University of Hartford, Microwave anecnoic chamber, Granted 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-82, Essex Marine Laboratory, Oil spill control facility, Granted 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-83, Consolidated Controls, Corp., Advanced Incinerator Methods, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-84, Kaman Aircraft, Forecasting model for research manpower, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-85, University of Bridgeport, Chemical and isotope shifts of elements, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-86, University of Bridgeport, Laser-Raman spectroscopy at high pressures, Granted 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-87, University of Connecticut, Mechanism of host plant selection, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-88, University of Hartford, Economic effects of long range urban programs, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-89, University of Connecticut, Nuclei for fog dissipation, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-90, Wesleyan University, Infrared spectroscopy of ring molecules, Granted 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-91, Wesleyan University, Photochemical and spectroscopic behavior of a rhodopsin model, Deferred 1967 December 15, Granted 1968 April 19 (Box 2)
  - P-92, Bloomfield Public Schools, Developmental status of kindergarten children, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-93, Yale University, Hydrothermal pressure system, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-94, Dunlap and Associates, Prototype program for technically trained personnel, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-95, Hamilton Standard, Regional clinical laboratory, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-96, Dunlap and Associates, Systems analysis of school bussing, Declined, 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-97, Dunlap and Associates, Municipal data processing in Connecticut, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-98, University of Connecticut, Innter city in crisis: Case in Connecticut, Declined 1967, December 15, Granted as P-98R 1968 January 19 (Box 2)
  - P-99, James S. Minges & Associates, Means of disposal of industrial wastes (Box 2)
  - P-100, TRC, Inc., Verification and refinement of Connecticut air pollution simulation model, Provisional award 1968 March 15 (Box 2)
  - P-101, McGuigan Engineering Co., Model disassembly line to handle efficiently unburned automobiles in Connecticut, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-102, University of Connecticut, Science technology and law, Deferred 1967 December 15, Declined 1968 February 16 (Box 2)
  - P-103, University of Connecticut, Connecticut flora for tumor inhibitors carcinogens, Granted 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-104, University of Connecticut, Theory of elementary particles, Declined 1967 December 15 (Box 2)
  - P-105, Health Dept., Refuse disposal methods, Deferred 1967 November 17, Withdrawn (Box 2)
  - P-106, Essex Marine Laboratory, Inc. Reproductive potential of American shad in Connecticut River, Granted 1968 March 15 (Box 2)
  - P-107, University of Bridgeport, Industrial problems in forming, cutting, and casting of materials, Granted 1968 January 19 (Box 2)
  - P-108, NERAC, Scientific and technical information search, Granted 1968 January 19 (Box 2)
  - P-109, UAC Research Labs, Marine mineral identification survey, Declined 1968 April 19, Granted 1968 May 24 (Box 2)
  - P-110, Probate Court Administration, Revision of Connecticut's succession and estate tax laws, Granted 1968 April 19 (Box 2)
  - P-111, University of Bridgeport, Venturi type air pollution control device, Granted 1968 April 19 (Box 2)
  - P-112, South Central Community College, Instrument to delimit and depict socieo-economic profiles of strudents, Refused 1968 November 9 (Box 2)
  - P-113, University of Bridgeport, Blood chemistry of Connecticut fish, Declined 1968 February 16 (Box 2)
  - P-114, University of Connecticut, Reading and psychomotor disability among mentally handicapped - average children, Granted 1968 January 19 (Box 2)
  - P-115, Central Connecticut State University, Absconding behavior among honey bees, Granted 1968 December 16 (Box 2)
  - P-116, University of Connecticut, Electron transport in semi-conductor heterojunctions, Declined 1968 June 21 (Box 2)
  - P-117, University of Connecticut, Secondary prevention of dependency, Withdrawn 1968 June 21 (Box 2)
  - P-118, Fairfield University, Biochemistry of Candida albicans and Candida stellatoidea, declined 1968 April 19 (Box 2)
  - P-119, St. Joseph's College, Organix geochemistry of Connecticut shales & sediments, Granted 1968 March 15 (Box 2)
  - P-120, University of Connecticut, Maturity & guilt in delinquent boys, Granted 1968 May 24 (Box 2)
  - P-121, University of Hartford, Organophosphate insecticides on cell metabolism, Declined 1968 February 16 (Box 2)
  - P-122, Connecticut bar Association, Legislation for Connecticut marriage & divorce laws, Declined 1968 April 19 (Box 2)
  - P-123, University of Connecticut, Wave propogation by direct finite element analysis, Granted 1968 April 19 (Box 2)
  - P-124, Hamilton Standard, Health screening for preschool children, Declined 1968 June 21 (Box 2)
  - P-126, University of Connecticut, Prediction of heart disease from behavioral variables, Declined 1968 April 19 (Box 2)
  - P-127, DeBell & Richardson, Industrial utilization of waste products from tobacco, Declined 1968 March 15 (Box 2)
  - P-128, University of Bridgeport, Dual x-ray emission-absorption spectrometer, Declined 1968 February 16 (Box 2)
  - P-129, Yale University, Allelopathy in vegetation dynamics of New England, Granted 1968 April 19 (Box 2)
  - P-130, University of Bridgeport, Addition of hydrogen bromide to 1-bromocyclo-alkenes, Declined 1968 April 19 (Box 2)
  - P-131, DeBell & Richardson, Highway signs and support structures for improved safety & lower cost, Withdrawn, 1968 October 30 (Box 2)
  - P-132, General Dynamics, Fish processing plant, Declined 1968 June 21 (Box 2)
  - P-133, General Dynamics, Deep water shellfish resources, Declined 1968 May 24 (Box 2)
  - P-134, Fairfield University, Commercial banks in Fairfield County & in New York State, Declined 1968 February 16 (Box 2)
  - P-135, Yale University, Amino acid sequence of amphibian hemoglobin, Declined 1968 April 19 (Box 2)
  - P-136, Hartford Jewish Community Center, Training of indigenous neighborhood people for owrk in day care center, Declined 1968 March 15 (Box 2)
  - P-137, Southern Connecticut State College, Teaching sex education in grades K through 9, Declined 1968 March 15 (Box 2)
  - P-138, Southern Connecticut State College, Ghetto kindergartners, Declined 1968 April 19 (Box 2)
  - P-139, Southern Connecticut State College, Sense training method for autistic children, Declined 1968 Marcy 15 (Box 2)
  - P-140, University of Connecticut, Minority employment, Granted 1969 March 13 (Box 2)
  - P-141, Raytheon Co., Estuary survey techniques for the monitoring & prediction of thermal elevation, Declined 1968 July 19 (Box 2)
  - P-142, Electric Boat, Survey of Thames River estuary, Declined 1968 November 15 (Box 3)
  - P-143, Fairfield University, Analysis of Bridgeport regional economy, Granted 1968 June 21 (Box 3)
  - P-144, Yale University, Chemistry of pine sawfly, Granted 1968 April 19 (Box 3)
  - P-145, Bycoski Co. Chemical conversion solid wastes, Withdrawn 1968 July 31 (Box 3)
  - P-146, Wesleyan University, Precision measurement physics, Declined 1968 May 24 (Box 3)
  - P-147, University of Connecticut, Nuclei for fog dissipation, Declined 1968 May 24 (Box 3)
  - P-148, University of Hartford, Delays in urban renewal project execution, Declined 1968 February 16 (Box 3)
  - P-149, Yale University, Upper Triassic dinisaurs of Connecticut Valley, Granted 1968 May 24 (Box 3)
  - P-150, Anaconda American Brass Co., Treatment of brass mill effluents, Granted 1968 June 21 (Box 3)
  - P-151, University of Hartford, Pilot highway noise study, Withdrawn 1968 June 21 (Box 3)
  - P-152, COSSECC, Computer assisted mathematics instruction, Granted 1968 June 21 (Box 3)
  - P-153, University of Connecticut, Mossbauer effect for the advancement of sensing and control, Deferred 1968 December 20, Declined 1969 February 13 (Box 3)
  - P-154, University of Connecticut, Science, technology and law: a survey and program, Granted 1968 April 19 (Box 3)
  - P-155, Yale University, Physiology of killifish of genus Fundulus, Granted 1968 June 21 (Box 3)
  - P-156, University of Connecticut, Immunological mechanisms of avian leukemia, Granted 1968 July 19 (Box 3)
  - P-157, University of Connecticut, PPBS for urban management, Withdrawn 1968 May 24 (Box 3)
  - P-158, University of Cionnecticut, Regional municipal information handling service for Connecticut municipal government & school systems, Granted 1968 July 19 (Box 3)
  - P-159, University of Connecticut, Parasitism, pathology & host response in bay scallop, Declined 1968 December 20 (Box 3)
  - P-160, Essex Marine Lab, Inc., Telemetered water quality monitoring network on Connecticut River, Declined 1968 July 17 (Box 3)
  - P-161, Yale University, Research lab for natural products studies, Granted 1960 March 13 (Box 3)
  - P-162, University of Connecticut, Study of cytochromes and flavoproteins, Granted 1968 May 24 (Box 3)
  - P-163, Child and Family Services of Connecticut, Use of counseling services by adoptive parents, Withdrawn 1968 June (Box 3)
  - P-164, Mystic Oceanographic Co., Aquiculture Experiment Station in Connecticut, Withdrawn, 1968 Octobe 23 (Box 3)
  - P-165, CBS Labs, Portable noise instrument, Granted 1968 August 16 (Box 3)
  - P-166, Raytheon Co., Portable noise Instrument, Declined 1968 August 16 (Box 3)
  - P-167. Bolt, Beranek, & Newman, Inc., Portable noise instrument, Declined 1968 August 16 (Box 3)
  - P-168, United Acoustic Consultants, Highway noise measurement, Declined 1968 November 15 (Box 3)
  - P-169, C.W. Lemmerman, Inc., Highway noise measurement, Declined 1968 November 15 (Box 3)
  - P-170, CBS Labs, Highway noise measurement, Granted 1968 November 15 (Box 3)
  - P-171, University of Hartford, Highway noise measurement, Declined 1968 November 15 (Box 3)
  - P-172, Eric J.W. Wood, Highway noise measurement, Declined 1968 November 15 (Box 3)
  - P-173, Wilbur Smith & Associate, Highway noise measurement, Declined 1968 November 15 (Box 3)
  - P-174, Instrument Consultants, Inc., Portable noise instrument, Declined 1968 August 16 (Box 3)
  - P-175, Vincent J. Skee, Portable noise insturment, Declined 1968 August 16 (Box 3)
  - P-176, University of Connecticut, Support of Behavioral Genetics Laboratories, Granted 1968 June 21 (Box 3)
  - P-177, University of Connecticut, Synthesis of muscle proteins, Declined 1968 July 19 (Box 3)
  - P-178, Yale University, Uric acid excretino in birds, Granted 1968 December 20 (Box 3)
  - P-179, Yale University, Controlled laser emission, Granted 1968 November 15 (Box 3)
  - P-180, University of Connecticut, Scanning electron microscope, Declined, 1968 July 19 (Box 3)